Fanny Fern and Ethel Parton Papers, 1805-1982
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Fanny Fern and Ethel Parton papers
1805-1982
Fern, Fanny and Ethel Parton
MS 117
15 boxes (7 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author, journalist, columnist, children's author, and humorist. Sara Payson Willis wrote for several small Boston magazines under the name Fanny Fern; numerous newspapers soon published her pieces. She had a regular weekly column in the New York Ledger and was one of the first woman columnists. Ethel Parton, granddaughter of Sara Willis and James Parton, worked as a writer and literary assistant, and at age 70 began writing children's books. Materials include extensive writings, correspondence, sketches, albums, and photographs.
Sara Payson Willis Parton, author and newspaper columnist better known as Fanny Fern, was born in Portland, Maine on July 9, 1811 to Nathaniel Willis and Hannah Parker. The fifth of nine children, Sara was educated in Boston and at Catharine Beecher's seminary in Hartford, Connecticut. While still in school she occasionally contributed to her father's periodical for children, Youth's Companion. Willis married Charles Eldredge in 1837. The couple had three daughters, Mary, Grace, and Ellen. After the death of Eldredge in 1846, Willis married Boston merchant Samuel P. Farrington, whom she divorced three years later. After several dismal employment ventures, in 1851 she began writing under the name Fanny Fern for several small Boston magazines. Numerous newspapers soon picked up her humorous pieces. A collection of her writings was published in 1853 as Fern Leaves from Fanny's Port-Folio, an immediate bestseller. She married historian and biographer James Parton in 1856. Fanny Fern's other publications include two novels, Ruth Hall (1855) and Rose Clark (1856); and six collections of her columns including Fresh Leaves (1857), Folly as It Flies (1859), Ginger-Snaps (1870), and Caper-Sauce (1872). Her astounding success led to a regular weekly column in the New York Ledger, making her America's first women columnist. Fern's works incorporated wit and impudence, dealing with such topics as domestic problems, equality between the sexes, the double standard of morality, the need for parents to respect willful children, and tomboys. She deplored excessive housework and too large families, encouraged women to seek wider fields of endeavor, poked fun at the august male, and criticized conventional religion. A suffrage supporter after 1858, Fern was a co-founder of New York City's pioneer woman's club, Sorosis, in 1868. Fanny Fern died of cancer in New York on October 10,1872.
Ethel Parton was born in New York on December 1,1862 to Mortimer Thomson (whose pen name was Q. K. Philander Doesticks) and Grace Eldredge, daughter of Sara Payson Willis Parton (Fanny Fern). Fanny Fern (her grandmother) and James Parton adopted her after the death of her mother. After Fanny Fern's death in 1872, James Parton married Ethel's aunt, Ellen Willis Eldredge, and the couple cared for Ethel along with their own children. Ethel was educated at home by James Parton, at the school of Jane Andrews, and at the Putnam Free School in Newburyport, Massachusetts. After high school Ethel worked for James Parton as "secretary, literary assistant, and occasional collaborator." She changed her surname to Parton on attaining her majority. After James Parton's death, Ethel was a correspondent for Youth's Companion (founded by her great-grandfather, Nathaniel Willis) and contributed verses and stories to St. Nicholas. At age 70, she began writing children's books. These included 6 titles, popularly known as "The Newburyport Chronicles" which were set in early 19th-century Newburyport: Melissa Ann (1932), Tabitha Mary (1933), Penelope Ellen (1936), Vinnie Applegay and Minnie Applegay (1937), Runaway Prentice (1939), The Lost Locket (1940), and The House Between (1943). Ethel Parton died in 1944.
The Fanny Fern and Ethel Parton Papers contain 7 linear feet and consist primarily of biographical data, including photographs, and material pertaining to the two women's writings. The collection is actually two separate but related sets of papers and have been arranged as such, beginning with the Fanny Fern Papers (SERIES I -IV), and continuing with the Ethel Parton Papers (SERIES V - IX). Types of material include correspondence, photographs and daguerreotypes, typescripts, printed matter, books, artwork, and memorabilia. The bulk of the papers date from 1850 to 1944, although many of Ethel Parton's typescripts are undated and it is unclear how many of them ever reached publication. Items that may be of particular interest to researchers include Fanny Fern's correspondence; photographs and drawings of Fanny Fern and members of her extended family; early editions of books by Fanny Fern; typescripts of all of Fanny Fern's New York Ledger articles (1856-72), compiled by Florence Bannard Adams, as well as a run of original issues of the New York Ledger (1871-72) containing pieces by Fanny Fern; "Popular Pundit: Fanny Fern and the Emergence of the American Newspaper Columnist," a paper by Smith College senior Elaine Gelles Breslaw '56; and typescripts of two unpublished biographies of Fanny Fern: "Fanny Fern: An Informal Biography" by Ethel Parton and "Who on Earth Was Fanny Fern?" by Ruth Sexton Sargent.
This collection is organized into nine series:
I. Fanny Fern Biographical Material
II. Fanny Fern Correspondence
III. Fanny Fern Memorabilia
IV. Fanny Fern Photographs
V. Fanny Fern Writings
VI. Ethel Parton Biographical Material
VII. Ethel Parton Correspondence
VIII. Ethel Parton Writings
IX. Ethel Parton Artwork
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
James Parton II donated the Fanny Fern Papers in 1951. He added to the collection on numerous occasions, most recently in 1992, and arranged for the Newburyport (MA) Public Library to donate the Ethel Parton Papers in 1978. Ruth Sexton Sargent gave the manuscript of her unpublished biography, "Who on Earth Was Fanny Fern?," to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1978.
Search Terms
Fern, Fanny, 1911-1872; Parton, Ethel, 1862-1944; Thomson, Mortimer, 1831-1875; Doesticks, Q.K. Philander, 1831-1875; Willis, Nathaniel Parker, 1806-1867; Parton, James, 1822-1891; Beecher, Catharine Esther, 1800-1878; Stowe, Harriet Beecher, 1811-1896; Newspapers--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources; Publishers and publishing--United States--History--Sources; American wit and humor--Women authors--19th century--Sources; Hartford Female Seminary (Hartford, Conn.)--History; New-York ledger--History; Parton family; Willis family; Women authors, American--19th century--Sources; Authors, American--19th century--Sources; Children's literature--Authorship--19th century--Sources; Feminists--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Satire, American--19th century--Sources; Women journalists--United States--History-19th century-Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
The papers of James Parton (1822-1891), Fanny Fern's third and last husband, and of James Parton II (b. 1912), her great-grandson, are in the Houghton Library at Harvard University and in the Harvard University Archives, located in the Nathan Marsh Pusey Library. The Olive Branch and the Boston True Flag, both of which Fern wrote for until she signed an exclusive contract with the New York Ledger in 1856, are located at the American Antiquarian Society in Worcester, Massachusetts.
- SERIES I. FANNY FERN BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1805-1982, .5 linear feet
  This series contains correspondence; legal documents, including those relating to Fern's divorce from Samuel Farrington and to the situation with the family of her first husband, Charles Eldredge; a genealogy and a family history; and articles, clippings and typescripts. There correspondence, legal documents, and articles and clippings pertain to Fanny Fern and her family; the typescripts are of the unpublished biography of Fanny Fern by Ruth Sexton Sargent and the senior thesis by Elaine Gelles Breslaw.
  [See also SERIES VIII. ETHEL PARTON WRITINGS]
- SERIES II. FANNY FERN CORRESPONDENCE 1829-1870, .25 linear feet
  The series includes correspondence with Catharine Beecher, Harriet Beecher Stowe, and Major Benjamin F. Butler, as well as with members of Fern's family.
- SERIES III. FANNY FERN MEMORABILIA undated, .25 linear feet
  This series consists of sketches; a memo book and a school album; a ceramic tile; and gloves lace, and fabric samples from Fern's wedding gown.
- SERIES IV. FANNY FERN PHOTOGRAPHS undated, .25 linear feet
  This series contains photographs, daguerreotypes, and a tintype of Fanny Fern and her family.
- SERIES V. FANNY FERN WRITINGS 1850-1884, 1.25 linear feet
  The series consists of contracts, financial statements, typescripts, newspapers, and books by Fanny Fern and by others. The books are early editions and are very fragile.
- SERIES VI. ETHEL PARTON BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1884-1980, .5 linear feet
  The series has in it correspondence pertaining to Ethel Parton material in the Newburyport (MA) Public Library, legal documents, photographs, clippings, memorabilia, and printed matter, as well as information about artist Nike Parton.
- SERIES VII. ETHEL PARTON CORRESPONDENCE 1885-1945, .25 linear feet
  This series contains correspondence with family, friends and acquaintances and is limited in scope.
- SERIES VIII. ETHEL PARTON WRITINGS 1896-1943, 2.75 linear feet
  This series consists of royalty statements, book reviews, contracts, correspondence, draft manuscripts and typescripts, notes, and fragments of writings. It includes a draft manuscript and a typescript of Parton's unpublished biography of Fanny Fern, "Fanny Fern: An Informal Biography."
- SERIES IX. ARTWORK 1891-1943, .25 linear feet
  The series contains sketches by Parton, and drafts of hand made Christmas cards she created based on Dutch tile designs.
- SERIES I. FANNY FERN BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - Nat'l Union Catalogue of Mss. Colls., data sheet, Parton family history1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Willis family genealogyundated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Last Will and Testament, Mary Eldredge1857 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Last Will and Testament and Letters Testamentary, Sara Payson Parton1873, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    [see also OVERSIZE MATERIAL]
  - Legal documents pertaining to Hezekiah Eldredge1805-49, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and legal documents, Farrington family1851-99, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to Florence Snow from Hope Willis Rathbun re: Fanny Fern and family matters1966-67 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles about Fanny Fern, including related correspondence1896-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings about Fanny Fern and other family members1874-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Typescript, "Popular Pundit: Fanny Fern and the Emergence of the American Newspaper Columnist," by Elaine Gellis Bradshaw1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Typescripts, "Who On Earth Was Fanny Fern?," by Ruth Sargentcirca 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
- SERIES II. FANNY FERN CORRESPONDENCE
  - Incoming
    - Beecher, Catharine1829, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Dana, Mary C.undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Dodge, Mary A.1869 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Eldredge, Charles to and from Fanny Fernundated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Flournoy, John James to Fanny Fern and Nathaniel P. Willis1830 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Greenwood, Grace1870 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Stowe, Harriet Beecher1868, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Torrey, E. Sutton to Fanny Fern1858 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing
    - Butler, Major Benjamin F.undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Eldredge, Ellen1871, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Florence Fern," undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Parton, Ethelundated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Van Cleve, Mrs.undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Willis, Richard S.1844 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Other
    - Greene, Mrs. E. Ferguson to Ellen E. Parton1899 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Willis, Katherine to Ellen Parton1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Willis, Mary to Nathaniel P. Willis1823 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Willis, Nathaniel P., letter and verseundated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- SERIES III. FANNY FERN MEMORABILIA
  - Memo booksundated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clipping and legal document, Town and Country Club of Newport, RIundated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sketches of Fanny Fern by Ellen Eldredge Partonundated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Tile with handwritingundated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - School albumundated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fabric sample from wedding dresscirca 1837 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Gloves and lace from wedding dresscirca 1837 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- SERIES IV. FANNY FERN PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Photocopies of photographs (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Photographs of Fanny Fern and extended familyundated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Daguerreotypes
    - Grace Eldredgeundated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hannah Parker Willisundated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Grace Eldredge Thomson and Mark Thomsonundated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Grace Eldredge Thomsonundated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Ellen and Grace Eldredgeundated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Ellen and Grace Eldredge as little girlsundated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Charles Eldredge, seated 1/2 face, full lengthundated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Charles Eldredge, profileundated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Charles Eldredge, seated facing left, 1/2 face, full lengthundated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Mark Thomson (?)undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Edward Willisundated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Ellen Eldredge with her grandfatherundated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified womanundated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Tintype: two Willis children (possibly Harry and Josephine Jenkins,children of Mary Willis Jenkins)undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- SERIES V. FANNY FERN WRITINGS
  - Contracts, publishers checklists, statements, and advertisements1850-73, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Articles by Fanny Fern for The New York Ledger: typescripts1855-72 (Box 4, Folder 2-19)
  - List of articles by Fanny Fern for the Olive Branch, the Boston True Flag, and the New York Ledger1851-62, located in bound volumes at the American Antiquarian Society, Worcester, MA (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - The New York LedgerFeb 1871 - Feb 1872, (Oversize box) (Box 5)
  - Books by Fanny Fern
    - Caper Sauce1872 (Box 6)
    - Fanny Fern: A Memorial Volume, ed. James Parton1873 (Box 6)
    - Fern Leaves From Fanny's Portfolio (6 copies)1853-54 (Box 6)
    - Ruth Hall: A Domestic Tale of the Present Time1855 (Box 6)
    - Folly as it Flies1859 (Box 7)
    - Fresh Leaves1857 (Box 7)
    - Ginger-Snaps1870 (Box 7)
    - Little Ferns1854 (Box 7)
    - Rose Clark1856 (Box 7)
    - Ruth Hall (2 copies)1855 (Box 8)
    - Play Day Book: New Stories for Little Folk1857 (Box 8)
    - Shadows and Sunbeams (2 copies)1881 (?), 1884 (Box 8)
  - Books by others
    - Life and Beauties of Fanny Fern by an anonymous author1855 (Box 8)
    - Rural Matters by Nathaniel Parker Willis1849 (Box 8)
    - The Watchman by J.A.M.1855 (Box 8)
- SERIES VI. ETHEL PARTON BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - Correspondence re: the Ethel Parton Papers in the Newburyport Public Library, Newburyport, MA1974-80 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Graduation memorabilia, typescripts, and autobiographical sketches1880-1934, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Dedication of Ethel Parton Reading Room at the Newburyport Public Library1905 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 80th birthday party at the Newburyport Public Library: photograph and card1942 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Clippings and correspondence re: name change5 Feb 1884, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Marriage certificate, Mortimer Thomson and Grace Eldgedge1861 (Box 9)
  - Silhouette of Ethel Parton by Frieda Castelhun1931 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia1865-68, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Draft manuscript for plaque inscription, Upper Green, Old Newbury, MA1895 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Photographs
    - Ethel Parton and brother, Mark Partonundated (glass plate negative) (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Ethel Partonundated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Parton family1862-79, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Thomson family1873-77, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Published article, "Great Auction Sale of Slaves" by Mortimer Thomson1859, and his obituary, 1875 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Ellen Willis Eldredge Parton: correspondence and memorabiliaundated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Nike Parton: resume, clippings, and printed matter1956-77, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
- SERIES VII. ETHEL PARTON CORRESPONDENCE
  - Family
    - Parton, Ellen W. E.1887, 1897 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Parton, Hugo1887-1931 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Parton, Jamesundated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Parton, Mabel1887 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Friends and acquaintances
    - Incoming
      - Cushing, Fanny1885 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Eckert, Robert P.1934 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Flower, Milton1939 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Hills, Laura1936, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Lawson, Marie A.1932, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Mulliken, Sarah E.1930, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Pearson, Edmund1912-80 (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Pederson, Rachel Field1938 (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - Ruchione, Alice1945 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Van Doren, Carl1939 (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - Withington, Anne1914 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Zlotnik, Mae W., to and from Ethel Parton1939 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Outgoing
      - Bailey, Alice W.1899 (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - Maynard, Harriet1937 (Box 10, Folder 18)
      - Stevens, E.N.1928 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- SERIES VIII. ETHEL PARTON WRITINGS
  - Royalty statements1939-43 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Reviews of books by Ethel Parton1931-37 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Book Club listings1936-43 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Contracts1931-43 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence
    - Publishers1930-43, undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Wilford, Jessie Douglas1931-43, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Published prose
    - Books, [See also Box 16]
      - The House Between 1943
        - Draft manuscriptundated (Box 11, Folder 1-10)
        - Typescriptundated (Box 11, Folder 11-15)
      - Melissa Ann (1931): typescript of preface, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Penelope Ellen and Her Friends (1936): notesundated (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - The Year Without a Summer (1945): draft manuscriptundated (Box 12, Folder 3-10)
    - Articles and stories
      - Various stories in St. Nicholas1896-1910 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - "The Author of Penelope Ellen," Young Wings1936 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - "The Launch of the 'Mariana'," Youth's Companion1896 (Box 12, Folder 13)
        [see OVERSIZE MATERIAL]
      - Other stories1899-1940, undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Unpublished prose (?)
    - "Art Enlivens the Way": draft manuscriptundated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - "A Bit of Recaptured History": draft manuscriptundated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - "At the Sign of the Proud Peacock": typescriptundated (incomplete) (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - "Charades": typescript and notesundated (Box 13, Folder 4-6)
    - "Dumb Immortals": typescriptundated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - "Fanny Fern: An Informal Biography"
      - Draft manuscriptcirca 1928 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Typescript (copy 1)undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Typescript (copy 2)undated (Box 13, Folder 10-12)
      - Typescript (copy 3)undated (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
      - Correspondence and notes1940, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - "Flower, Fruit and Fancy": typescriptundated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - "Jan Vinges' Pea Patch": typescriptundated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - "Nothing to Wear": typescriptundated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - "Pigs and Peacocks," undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - "The Pocket Princess": typescriptundated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - "Peter Duponceau": typescriptundated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - "Peter's Luck": typescriptundated (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - "Three Teachers": typescriptundated (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - "When the Great Were Little": typescriptundated (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified fragmentsundated (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Published and unpublished verse
    - "The Ballad of the Borrowing Lady": draft manuscriptundated (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - "Children and Childish Fancies": draft manuscript and typescriptsundated (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - "Colonial period": notes and typescriptsundated (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - "Gift Verses": draft manuscripts1939-40 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - "Revolutionary period": draft manuscripts and typescriptsundated (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
    - "The White Cub": draft manuscriptundated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous verseundated (Box 15, Folder 4-10)
    - Unidentified fragmentsundated (Box 15, Folder 11-22)
- SERIES IX. ARTWORK
  - Sketches1891-93, undated (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Drawings and verse for "Delft tile Christmas cards," 1932-43 (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Books by Ethel Parton, added to the collection in 2005 (Box 16-17)
    - The House Between: A Story of the 1850s, 1943 (2 copies) (Box 16-17)
    - Melissa Ann: A Little Girl of the Eighteen Twenties, 1931 (Box 16-17)
    - The Mule of the Parthenon and Other New Stories of Ancient Greece, 1932 (Box 16-17)
    - Penelope Ellen and Her Friends: Three Little Girls of 1840, 1936 (Box 16-17)
    - Runaway Apprentice: The Story of Jeffrey, Susan, Tris, and Tibby in the Year 1800, 1939 (2 copies) (Box 16-17)
    - Tabitha Mary: A Little Girl of 1810, 1933 (3 copies) (Box 16-17)
    - The Year Without a Summer: A Story of 1816, 1945 (Box 16-17)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL
  - Letters Testamentary, Sara Payson Parton (Fanny Fern)1873 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Legal documents pertaining to Hezekiah Eldredge1878, undated (Map-case Flat file)
  - Contract between Sara Eldredge (Fanny Fern) and Derby Miller1853 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Marriage annullment between Sara Farrington (Fanny Fern) and Samuel Farrington1853 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Youth's Companion10 September 1896 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Letters from John Flournoy to Sara P. Willis (Fanny Fern) and Nathaniel Willis, her father1830 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Marriage certificate, Mortimer Thomson and Grace Eldgedge1861 (Map-case Flat file)
  - "Notice" by Samuel Farrington in The Bee25 Feb 1851 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Portland Transcript12 December 1852 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Petition of James Parton and Ellen Eldredge Parton to the Honorable Senate and House of Representatives of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts14 Feb 1876 (Map-case Flat file)